Guide to the Librarians Assembly records, 1972-[ongoing] UA.08.02.0003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Librarians Assembly records
1972-[ongoing]
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Librarians Assembly (Duke University) (1974-)
UA.08.02.0003
7.75 Linear Feet
The Librarians Assembly (LA) of Duke University is the staff association for professional librarians at Duke University. The Librarians Assembly records contains materials related to the formation, organization, and activities of the LA.
Access Restrictions
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Provenance
The Librarians Assembly Records were received by the Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, as a series of transfers, described in this finding aid.
Historical Note
The Librarians Assembly (LA) is the staff association for professional librarians at Duke University. Its purpose is to serve as an advocate for excellence in librarianship; to promote the interest and participation of its members in the affairs of the libraries, the University, and the profession at large; and to make recommendations concerning planning, policies, and procedures to appropriate library and University officials.
In 1970, then University Librarian Benjamin Powell appointed the Branson Committee (led by Barbara Branson) to compile and present the results of a study of professional staff in academic libraries in the United States, including information on status, salary scales, and fringe benefits. The committee was formed in response to efforts to formalize the status of professional librarians by the University's Personnel Office (now Human Resources). These efforts would have categorized professional librarians without clear criteria and without input from the University Librarian or library staff, and would have offered significantly different benefits packages based on rank and status. The Branson Comittee's report, submitted in January 1971, provided information about library staff at other academic institutions and offered recommendations for Duke librarians. The report suggested a system of promotion based on merit and experience, allowing librarians to advance in rank while holding the same position; the report also recommended that library staff attempt to join the Academic Council.
In spring of 1972 Benjamin Powell appointed two committees, the Bylaws Committee and the Committee on Professional Staff Structure (COPSS). The Bylaws Committee was charged to write a bylaw which defines the place of the professional library staff in the academic community, while COPSS was charged with devising a structure for the professional staff of the University Libraries and spelling out steps for promotion in rank. COPSS wrote several documents, "Criteria for Appointment of Professional Librarians," Ranking Structures for Duke University Librarians," "Committee on Appointment and Promotion," and "Duke University Librarians Assembly," which was used as the background for the later "Bylaws of the Duke University Librarians Assembly." In 1973, the Board of Trustees of Duke University approved a bylaw recognizing the academic and professional status of librarians in the university. Later that same year, the Ad Hoc Ranking Committee, nominated by COPSS, began an initial ranking of the professional staff in Perkins Library (now Duke University Libraries).
On December 4, 1973, the Librarians Assembly was formally created following a unanimous vote of professional librarians from the Perkins and Medical Library systems. In May 1974, the Librarians Assembly and Benjamin Powell approved "Ranking Structure for Duke University Librarians," "Duke University Librarians Assembly," and "Committee on Appointment and Promotion." These papers were approved by then-Provost Frederic Cleaveland in December 1974 and became fully effective. The Executive Committee, Bylaws Committee, the Committee on Appointment and Promotion, and the Professional Affairs Committee were designated as standing committees.
Throughout 1975 the Bylaws Committee, the Committee on Appointment and Promotion, and the Committee to Study the Professional Library Staff Fringe Benefits worked to create and strengthen regulations and documentation on the self-governance of the professional library staff. The Law Librarians voted to join the Librarians Assembly in June of 1975. In summer of 1976, the Assembly Bylaws were declared to be in effect and it was also determined that a librarians must have a professional degree from an ALA accredited library school or equivalent foreign degree in order to have a professional appointment. The Bylaws Committee continued to revise the Assembly regulations throughout the 1970s, with input from the library directors and the Office of the Provost.
In 1983 the Fuqua School of Business Library, now the Ford Library, elected to join the Librarians Assembly; in early 1984 the Executive Committee unanimously approved changes to the Bylaws to include the Fuqua School of Business Library in the Librarians Assembly.
Until at least the mid-1990s, the Librarians Assembly had bi-monthly meetings that included a program of professional interest to librarians as well as LA business. Since its formation, the Librarians Assembly has held an annual business meeting at the end of the Spring semester, usually in mid or late May.
Collection Overview
The Librarians Assembly records contains materials related to the formation, organization, and activities of the Librarians Assembly of Duke University. Materials include minutes, reports, correspondence, flyers, regulations and bylaws, and subject files. Topics covered include the assembly's regulations and governing documents; issues surrounding appointment and promotion; salaries and benefits for librarians; the academic status of librarians; staff issues such as parking and grievance producres; and other subjects. The collection includes materials from the formation of the Librarians Assembly through the early 2000s.
Library administration; Library employees -- North Carolina -- Durham.; Universities and colleges -- Employees -- Salaries, etc.; Promotions -- North Carolina -- Durham; Librarians Assembly (Duke University) (1974-); Duke University Libraries; Duke University. Medical Center. Library; Duke University.. J. Michael Goodson Law Library; Fuqua School of Business (Duke University). Ford Library
- General Files, 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes general materials from the Librarians' Assembly not solely or specifically related to a particular committee. Includes minutes of Librarians' Assembly meetings, especially the annual business meeting; files created by presidents and officers of the Librarians' Assembly; reports; memoranda; and other materials. Topics covered include promotion; continuing appointment; the assembly's regulations and governing documents; committee appointments and work; salaries and salary increases; benefits for librarians; and many other subjects.
  - Minutes, 1.1
    Topics covered include issues related to promotion; continuing appointment; LA regulations and documentation related to rank, promotion, and continuing appointment; library representation on the Academic Council; the work of the Professional Affairs Committee (PAC); greivance procedures; salaries and salary increases; benefits for librarians; creation of a librarian's handbook; and other subjects.
    Materials in this series are arranged chronologically.
    - Index to Minutes, 1973-1979 (Box 1)
    - Index to Assembly Minutes, 1973-1981 (Box 1)
    - Index to Minutes, 1973-1984; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1973-1975, 1977, 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - Minutes and Agendas, 1980-1983 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, Notes, working papers, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1984-1986 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - Minutes and Handbook for Librarians, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, 1992-1998 (Box 2)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted until 2023.
    - Minutes, 1996-1998 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, 1998-2000 (Box 3)
      Restricted until 2025.
    - Minutes, 2000-2002 (Box 3)
      Restricted until 2027.
    - Minutes, 2000-2012
      Restricted until 2037.
  - President's and Officers' Files, 1.2
    Includes files from LA Presidents Winston Broadfoot and Lawrence Kline regarding benefits; from other officers regarding regulations and bylaws; scheduling and agendas; correspondence regarding matters discussed in meetings; resignations from and appointments to committees; timeline of academic governance for Duke Librarians 1960s-1980s in Kitty Porter's notes; meeting minutes; and other subjects. Many files include handwritten notes.
    - Broadfoot Communication, 1973-1978 (Box 3)
    - Broadfoot Correspondence, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Kline Memos and Correspondence, 1972-1976 (Box 3)
    - Kline Memoranda, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Presidency, 1976-1981 (Box 3)
    - Janie Morris: President's Notes, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
    - Jane Snyder: President's Notes, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Branson: President's Notes, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - (Eisenbeis) Bergholz: President's Notes, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - Bergholz: President's Notes, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - Byrd: President's Notes, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - Kitty Porter: President's Notes, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
    - Reed: President's Notes, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Roberta Schaafsma: Misc. Documents, 2003-2006 (Box 4)
      Restricted until 2031.
  - General Files, 1.3
    Includes subject files created and maintained by a variety of officers of the Librarians Assembly. Topics covered include the Libraries' liaison to the Academic Council; discussion of issues related to considering librarians as faculty; parking for library staff; the assembly's regulations and governing documents; issues around continuing appointment and promotion; policies and policy changes; fringe benefits; filling vacant positions with professional or paraprofessional staff; member lists; and other subjects.
    Materials in this series are arranged alphabetically.
    - Academic Council/Librarian membership/status, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
    - Academic Council, 1972-1987 (Box 4)
    - Academic Freedom for Librarians, Statement, 1972 (Box 4)
    - AUL Search - Administrative Services, 1978 (Box 4)
    - AUL Search - Collection Development, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Barchas Collection, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Calendar, 1981 (Box 4)
    - A Chronological History, undated (Box 4)
    - Collective bargaining definitions and bibliography, undated (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1983 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence with other Assemblies, Library Association of UNC, 1975-1987 (Box 4)
    - Directories, 1992-1993, 1995-1997 (Box 4)
    - Draft Policies, Perkins Library, 1975-1981 (Box 4)
    - Electronic vote items, 2008
      Items voted on in 2008 related to Promotion System for Term Appointment Librarians and Grievance Procedures.
      Restricted until 2033.
    - Faculty Commons Issue, 1992-1994 (Box 4)
    - Filling Profesional Vacancies, 1975-1986 (Box 4)
    - Flyers, Minutes, Memos, and Policies, 1975-1977 (Box 4)
    - Fringe Benefits for Librarians, 1966-1976 (Box 5)
    - Librarians' Benefits - Correspondence and Handbook, 1973-1980 (Box 5)
    - Library Specialist Documentation, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Funeral Leave, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Survey on Continuing Appointments, 1985 (Box 5)
    - General File, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    - General File, 1991-1992 (Box 5)
    - General File, 1992-1994 (Box 5)
    - Government Correspondence, 1974-1980 (Box 5)
    - Governing Documents, 1975-1982 (Box 5)
    - Governing Documents, 1986-1994 (Box 5)
    - Governing Documents, 2002-2011
      Restricted until 2036.
    - Graduate Faculty, 1972-1977 (Box 5)
    - Grievance, 1987-1988 (Box 6)
    - Grievance Procedure, 1988-1989 (Box 6)
    - Handbook for Librarians, 1988-1989 (Box 6)
    - Harvard's Ranking System, undated (Box 6)
    - Librarians Association at the University of NC at Chapel Hill, 1987-1989 (Box 6)
    - Library Director Search, 1975-1985 (Box 6)
    - Lists of members: Material used to formulate prof. staff lists, 1978 (Box 6)
    - Lists of members: Lists of professional librarians compiled, 1978-1979 (Box 6)
    - Lists of members: Extra lists of professional librarians updated through Apil 24, 1979 (Box 6)
    - Lists of members: Material used to formulate 1979 member lists (Box 6)
    - Lists of members: Official copies of LA member lists, 1978-1980 (Box 6)
    - Lists of members: Official copies, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Lists of members: Lists of professional librarians, 1977-1981 (Box 6)
    - Lists of members: Official copies, 1981 (Box 6)
    - Lists of members: Official copies, 1982-1985 (Box 6)
    - Lists of members, 1985-1988 (Box 6)
    - Lists of members, 1992-1993 (Box 6)
    - Meetings, 1992-1994 (Box 6)
    - Membership, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
    - Merit and Other Evaluations, 1976-1984 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1972-1978 (Box 7)
    - New Staff Orientation, 1987-1989 (Box 7)
    - Parking, 1976-1983 (Box 7)
    - Parking, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Parliamentary Procedure, undated (Box 7)
    - Part-time Librarians, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Perkins Constit. Group, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Professional Status Issues, 1975-1980 (Box 7)
    - Professional Status Issues: Part-time, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
    - Proxy Vote Form, undated (Box 7)
    - Regulations, 1972-1980 (Box 7)
    - Regulations: Original Documents for Reproduction Master Copies, 1973-1980 (Box 7)
    - Regulations: Bylaws 1976 approved ed. Extra Copies (Box 7)
    - Regulations: Regulations and Bylaws, 1980-1981 (Box 7)
    - Regulations: Staff Responses, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Regulations, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
    - Regulations: Fuqua School, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Safety Issues, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Salaries, 1973-1988 (Box 7)
    - Secretary Information, 1980-1986 (Box 7)
    - Social Event, 1988 (Box 7)
    - Speakers (guest), 1978-1984 (Box 7)
    - Staff Lists and Structure, 1977-1986 (Box 8)
    - Stationery, undated (Box 8)
    - Stipends, 1978-1979 (Box 8)
    - Support of Professional Activities, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Support Staff Reward Program, 1988 (Box 8)
    - University Bylaws Article XXIV. The University Librarians, undated (Box 8)
    - University Correspondence, 1975-1979 (Box 8)
    - University Librarians, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
    - Robert's Rule of Order, 1970 (Box 16)
    - Parliamentary Procedure at a Glance, 1971 (Box 16)
- Executive Committee, 2
  Includes minutes, correspondence, and notes from both the Executive Committee meeting and Librarians Assembly meetings; topics covered are largely the same as the general files.
  - Meeting Minutes, 1973-1976 (Box 8)
  - Minutes, 1976-1978 (Box 8)
  - Minutes, 1977-1980 (Box 8)
  - Minutes, 1977-1987 (Box 8)
  - Agenda, 1977-1988 (Box 8)
  - Minutes, 1978-1980 (Box 9)
  - Minutes and Meeting Agendas, 1979-1980 (Box 9)
  - Minutes (Working Documents), 1980-1982; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Minutes, 1980-1984 (Box 9)
  - Records (ExCom., Assembly, Corresp., etc.), 1980-1984 (Box 9)
  - Minutes, 1981-1982 (Box 9)
  - Minutes, 1984-1986 (Box 9)
  - Executive Committee, 1985; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Records (ExCom., Assembly, Corresp., etc.), 1985-1989 (Box 9)
  - Minutes, 1986-1987 (Box 10)
  - Minutes, 1987-1988 (Box 10)
  - Minutes, 1988-1989 (Box 10)
  - Minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 10)
  - Minutes and Agendas, 1989-1990 (Box 10)
  - Records, 1992-1994 (Box 10)
  - Executive Committee, 1993-1994 (Box 10)
  - Meeting Summaries, 1996-1997 (Box 10)
    Restricted until 2022.
  - Meeting Minutes, 1998-2000 (Box 10)
  - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, 2009-2012
- Bylaws Committee, 3
  Includes drafts, revisions, and correspondence related to the bylaws and regulations of the Librarians Assembly.
  - Regulations Revisions, 1977-1980 (Box 10)
  - Extra Regs. with Cover Letter, 1980-1981 (Box 10)
  - Regulations drafts (1 of 3), 1981 (Box 10)
  - Regulations drafts (2-3 of 3), 1981; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Regulations Revisions, 1981-1983 (Box 11)
  - Regulations draft, 1982 (Box 11)
  - Requests for Changes, 1983-1986 (Box 11)
  - Regulations Revisions, 1985 (Box 11)
  - Bylaws Committee, 1978-1987 (Box 11)
  - Bylaws Committee, 1997 (Box 11)
  - Bylaws Reports, 1999-2012
- Committee on Appointment and Promotion, 4
  Includes materials related to the Committee on Appointment and Promotion (CAP) and related groups such as the Ad Hoc Criteria Committee. Materials include reports on the history of CAP; rationale for decisions made in creating and structuring CAP policy; policy drafts; correspondence and memoranda regarding the work of CAP and its decision-making process; notes on a proposed external review commmittee for CAP; criteria for CAP decisions; and other subjects.
  These materials do not include any personal employment information.
  - Continuing Appointment Papers, 1971-1977 (Box 11)
  - CAP Questions, 1974-1980 (Box 11)
  - CAP, 1974-1983 (Box 11)
  - Committee on Appointment of Promotion, 1974-1987 (Box 11)
  - Annual Evaluation Form and policy documents, 1977 (Box 11)
  - Continuing Appointment, 1977-1978 (Box 11)
  - Proposed CAP Amendments, 1979 (Box 12)
  - External Review Committee for Promotion and Cont. Appt., 1979-1980 (Box 11)
  - Memo from A. Hirsch on re: CAP and Promotion Criteria, 1980 (Box 11)
  - CAP, 1980-1981 (Box 12)
  - CAP, 1982-1983 (Box 12)
  - CAP, 1983-1984 (Box 12)
  - Superseded Papers, 1984 (Box 12)
  - Continuing Appointment, 1984-1985 (Box 12)
  - CAP, 1984-1985 (Box 12)
  - CAP, 1986-1987 (Box 12)
  - CAP, 1987-1988 (Box 12)
  - CAP, 1988-1989 (Box 12)
  - CAP Reviews (Promotions), 1989-1990 (Box 12)
  - CAP Papers, 1990-1991 (Box 12)
  - CAP Papers, 1991-1992 (Box 12)
  - CAP, 1993-1994 (Box 12)
  - CAP Committee Reports, 1998-2012
- Professional Affairs Committee, 5
  Includes reports, correspondence, memoranda, and other materials related to the work of the Professional Affairs Commmittee. Topics covered include the academic status of librarians; librarian salaries; fringe benefits, especially tuition benefits; program planning and promotion; research on tenure for librarians; and other subjects.
  - Benefits, Status, Salaries memb. on Academic Council, 1972-1975 (Box 12)
  - Benefits, Salaries, Old Statistics, 1974-1977 (Box 12)
  - PAC, 1975-1988 (Box 12)
  - Minutes, 1976, 1979 (Box 12)
  - Program and "Lunch and Table" Ideas, 1977-1978 (Box 12)
  - PAC, 1978-1979 (Box 12)
  - Continuing Education, 1978-1979 (Box 12)
  - Report on Administrative Stipends, 1979 (Box 12)
  - PAC, 1979-1980 (Box 12)
  - Handouts for New Staff - Correspondence, 1980-1988 (Box 12)
  - PAC, 1981-1982 (Box 12)
  - PAC, 1981-1984 (Box 13)
  - PAC, 1982-1983 (Box 13)
  - PAC, 1984-1985 (Box 13)
  - Publicity, 1984-1986 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 13)
  - PAC, 1985-1986 (Box 13)
  - Lunch and Talk, 1986-1987 (Box 13)
  - Lynn Carney, 1986 (Box 13)
  - PAC, 1986-1987 (Box 13)
  - Distribution List for Events, 1986 (Box 13)
  - PAC, 1990-1992 (Box 13)
  - PAC, 1993-1994 (Box 14)
  - Lectures, 1986-1997 (Box 14)
  - Subcommittee on Tenure: Literature Review, 1997-1998 (Box 14)
  - Subcommittee on Tenure: Survey Responses, 1998 (Box 14)
  - PAC Reports, 1998-2012
  - PAC, 2009-2012
- Other Committees, 6
  This series contains materials related to non-standing committees and groups within the Librarians Assembly, including lists of committee appointees, committee reports, and files related to individual committees including the Ad Hoc Criteria Committee (related to CAP), the Branson Committee that provided the guiding recommendations for the Librarians Assembly, the Patriot Act Task Force convened in 2004, and LA observers to other committees such as the Library Council, among others.
  Materials in this series are arranged by type of committee, then chronologically.
  - Committee Lists, 1978-1980 (Box 14)
  - Committee Lists, 1980, 1982 (Box 14)
  - Commitees and Observers Lists, 1982-1983 (Box 14)
  - Committee Lists, 1974-1989 (Box 14)
  - Committee Assignments/Observers, 1989-1993 (Box 14)
  - Membership, 1977 (Box 14)
  - Membership, 1974-1981 (Box 14)
  - Committee Members, Observers, 1974-2002 (Box 14)
  - Committee Reports, 1974-1979 (Box 14)
  - Annual Reports, 1979-1980 (Box 14)
  - Observer/Committee Reports May 20, 1999 Business Meeting (Box 14)
    Restricted until 2024.
  - Committee Reports, 1999-2010
    Restricted until 2035.
    Reports and documents of LA committees and committee observers, including LA committees Patriot Act Task Force, Future Focus Working Group, and Nominating Committee, and committee observers to the Library Council, Academic Council, and Graduate Faculty Council.
  - Committees, 2007-2012
  - Documents to Screening Committees, 1978 (Box 14)
  - Ad Hoc Criteria Committee, 1980 (Box 14)
  - Ad Hoc Criteria Committee, 1980 (Box 14)
  - Branson Committee Report, 1971 (Box 14)
  - FLIP Agenda/Minutes, 1988-1990 (Box 15)
  - FLIP Task Force on the Role of Professional Librarians, 1988-1989 (Box 15)
  - Library Council, 1978 (Box 15)
  - Library Council, 1979-1988 (Box 15)
  - Library Council Minutes and Materials, 1990-1991 (Box 15)
  - Library Council, 1993-1994 (Box 15)
  - Library Council Reports, 1996-1999 (Box 15)
  - Librarians Assembly Nominating Committee, 1975-1989 (Box 15)
  - Scholarship Committee, 1976-1988 (Box 15)
  - University Committees Observers, 1972-1987 (Box 15)
- Support Staff Council, 7
  This series contains materials collected by the Librarians Assembly related to the Support Staff Council, a related organization for staff of the libraries on the bi-weekly payroll. Topics covered include parking, attendance and scheduling policies, SSC committee membership and appointments, and other subjects.
  - Minutes, 1978-1979 (Box 15)
  - Minutes, 1978-1987 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1979-1986 (Box 16)
  - Minutes, 1980-1985 (Box 16)